大家好
hello everyone
很高兴在 ViteConf 再次见到大家
it feels so good to be back here and see you again at the ViteConf
今天我的主题是集合论
and today my topic is The Set Theory
我知道这会稍微有些不明所以，但别担心
I know it's a bit random but don't worry
稍后我会慢慢解释
I'll try to explain that later
让我先简单介绍一下自己
so let me first introduce myself a bit
我叫 Anthony Fu
my name is Anthony Fu
我是 Vite, Vue 和 Nuxt 的核心团队成员
and I'm a core team member of Vite, Vue and Nuxt
我还创建了一些开源项目
I'm also creating a few open source project
我是 Vitest, Slidev, UnoCSS, VueUse, 和 Elk 的作者
and I'm a creator of Vitest, Slidev, UnoCSS, VueUse, and Elk
我目前在 NuxtLabs 的框架团队工作
I'm currently working at NuxtLabs on the framework team
回到我们的主题
so back to our topic
作为一个在开源领域工作了一段时间的人
as someone who has been working on open source for a while
并以此为生
and made a living
我不得不说开源
I have to say that open source
是非常有趣且值得做的
is so much fun and rewarding
我相信你们中的很多人想为开源做贡献
I believe that many of you wanted to contribute to open source
或已经在做了
or already doing so
然而，有许多因素会影响
however there are so many factors that affect
一个开源项目是否能够流行或成功
if an open source project could become popular or successful
这取决于你如何定义它
depends on how you define it
例如代码质量、文档、社区
for example the quality of code, the documentations, the community
市场营销等等
the marketing and so on
所有这些都是重要的并且彼此相关
all of them are important and related to each other
没有一个可以让开源项目成功的黄金法则
there isn't a golden rule to make open source projects successful
所以对于今天的主题
so for today's topic
我想分享一些我的经验
I would like to share some my experience
和在创建和维护开源项目方面的想法
and ideas on creating and maintaining open source projects
结合一些我从社区中学到的知识
combining with some observations that I have learned from the community
希望能帮助你开始自己的
hopefully it can help you to start your own
开源之旅
open source journey
或找到一些新的想法来改进你现有的项目
or find some new ideas to improve your existing project
这将是一个系列的演讲
this is going to be a series of talk
今天我想开始第一个主题
and today I would like to start the very first one of them
今天的主题有点抽象
so today's topic is a bit abstract one
我称之为集合论
I'd call it The Set Theory
一种思考项目规划
a way of thinking on planning
项目方向和路线图的方法
the directions and the roadmap of your project
假设我们已经有了一个开源项目
so let's say we already have a open source project
或者计划创建一个
or planning to create one
稍微实际一些
to be a little bit practical
我们可能希望获得一定数量的用户
we might want to gain certain amount of adoption
或者我们只是希望
or just we want
更多的人使用或享受我们的努力成果
more people to use or enjoy our hard work
我们需要考虑的是
one of the things to consider
如何建立用户画像
is how we picturing our target users
例如，我的工具是面向终端用户还是开发者
for example is my tool for end users or developers
是Vue用户还是React用户等
is that for Vue users or React users etc
已知在我们所有的目标用户中
so we know that the fact that amounts all of our target user
只有一部分人会成为我们的真实用户
only a portion of them will become our actual user
为了获得更多的用户
in order to get more uses to our project
我们可以尝试将
we could try to convert
更多潜在用户转化为真实用户
more potential uses to the actual users
也许通过一些市场营销或润色
maybe by doing some marketing or polishing
在这种情况下
in that case the amount of
目标用户的数量就成为了
target user you have accurate becomes the upper limit
你可能拥有的真实用户的上限
of how many accurate user you could possibly have
另一方面
on the other hand
我们还可以尝试找到
we can also try to find a way to expand
扩展我们的目标用户群的方法
our target user to include more people
在这个思路下，让我们举一些例子
under this idea let's take at some examples that
看看我们如何能做到这一点
how we could do that
第一个我想给你们展现的例子是
the first example I'm going to show you is actually
我在2019年做的第一个开源项目
my first open source project back in 2019
这个项目叫做 VS Code-vue-i18n-ally
the repo name is called VS Code-vue-i18n-ally
它是一个 VS Code 插件，帮助 Vue 开发者处理国际化 (i18n)
it's a VS Code extension for helping vue developers to working on i18n
比如在代码中预览翻译
like preview translations in code
或者管理每种语言的密钥等
or manage keys for each language etc
这是扩展的截图
this is the screenshot of the extensions
展示了基本功能
that shows the basic feature
但扩展本身并不是我们今天的主题
well the extension itself isn't our main topic it today
当时我渴望这个项目
at that times I am eager to make this project as
尽可能流行，并想在开源社区中证明自己
popular as I want to prove myself in open source world
我非常高兴当我获得了
I'm super happy when I got uh
第一个100和200个GitHub stars
the first 100 and 200 stars on Github
并收到了社区的赞赏
and received their appreciations from the community
之后我开始寻求更高的目标
after that I start to seek for higher goals
当时我梦想能够全职参与开源
back then I was dreaming to work full times open source
就像尤雨溪那样
for example like Even you
所以我的野心是做一些
so my ambitions was to make something
和Vue一样流行的东西
popular as popular as Vue
然后我突然意识到
then I suddenly saw
我的项目和Vue的根本区别
the fundamental difference between my projects and Vue
这直接反映在项目名称上
there directly reflects on the project names
看下我的项目名称
look at my project names
我们看到名称很长，并由多个部分组成
we saw that there is quite long and composed by multiple parts
让我们每个部分拆解来看
let's break it down to see part by part
首先，我们知道这是一个 VS Code 插件
so first we know that it's a VS Code extension
这意味着只有 VS Code 用户会用这个插件
so basically means that only VS Code user would use this extension
我们可以画一个圈，代表 VS Code 用户
we could draw a circle indicating the VS Code user here
然后对于Vue
and then for Vue
因为它是建立在我的需求之上的
uh because it's built on base on my need
我们也可以画一个Vue的圈
um then we could have a Vue circle as well
最后，这是一个国际化工具
and then finally this is the helper for internalization
这意味着
meaning that
并不是所有的Vue用户都会使用这个扩展
not all of the Vue users would use this extensions
所以我们可以画另一个i18n的圈
so we could draw another circle for i18n
然后我们发现
and then we find that
我们的目标用户被限制在这三个圈的交集内
our target users are limited inside the intersection of these three circles
意味着
meaning that
只有在做i18n应用程序的Vue开发者
only Vue developers who are working on an i18n app
并且正好使用 VS Code
that happen to choose VS Code
作为他们的编辑器
as their editor
才会尝试这个扩展
would ever try this extension
这听起来相当有限
that sounds quite limited
这我称之为交集现象
this is the phenomenon I call the intersections
在深入探讨解决方案之前
before we dive into the solution
让我们看看这个图
let's have a look at this graph
其他的交集意味着什么
what would the other intersections mean
我们很快就能意识到
we could soon realize that
VS Code 和 Vue 的交集
the intersection between VS Code and Vue
实际上是 Volar
is actually Volar
或者当时是Vetur
or Vetur at that time
就是 VS Code 对 Vue 的 IDE 支持
the VS Code IDE support for Vue
因此我们知道
as the result, we know that
Vetur 和 Volar 有很大的用户群
Vetur and Volar have a huge user base
因为 Vue 和 VS Code 都有
because both Vue and VS Code have
足够大的社区
huge enough communities
使得它们的交集足够大
making the intersections large enough
同样地
similarly
我们看到 Vue 和 i18n 的交集
we see that the intersection between Vue and i18n
是像 vue-i18n 这样的项目
are the projects like Vue-i18n
也非常受欢迎
which are also super popular
所以当涉及到 VS Code 和 i18n 的交集
so when it comes to the intersection between VS Code and i18n
我们看到当时似乎没有这样的项目
we see that there seems to be no such project at that time
直截了当的想法
a straightforward thinking
可以做一个，对吧？
that be that one right
实际上，我们可以
in practice, we could
尝试做一个扩展与Vue解耦
try to make the extension decoupled from Vue
这样它也可以被其他框架使用
so it could be used by the other frameworks as well
简而言之，让它变得通用
in short, let's make it universal
通过打破这些圈子，扩大交集
by breaking the set circles and expanding the intersections
我就是这样做的
and that's how I did
我花了一些时间做了一个大的重构
I took some time to do a huge refactor
设计了一个插件接口，使核心功能变得通用
designed a plugin interface to make the core feature universal
在1.0版本我将项目名称从 vue-i18n-ally 改为 i18n-ally
at 1.0 I renamed the projects from Vue-i18n-Ally to i18n-Ally
从一个仅限 Vue 的扩展
from a Vue-only extension
变为支持多个框架的 VS Code 通用 i18n 助手
to a universal i18n helper for VS Code that supports a wide range of frameworks
现在支持 React 和 Angular
now say React and Angular
它还支持一些后端框架
it also includes backend frameworks
如Laravel，Ruby on Rails，甚至是一些本地框架
like Laravel, Ruby on Rails, and even native target frameworks
它们是可定制和可扩展的
and they are customizable and extendable as needed
所以谈到数量
so when it comes to numbers
我们可以清楚地看到
we can clearly see
在我们发布时的star数有显著增加
a step increase of our stars at the times we doing the release
在发布的一个月内，star数几乎翻倍
the stars almost doubled in a month at that time
所以，让我们谈谈我们的老朋友 Vite
so, um, let's talk a bit about our old friend Vite
这是一个故事
this is a story
可能大多数人已经熟悉了
that's probably most of you are already familiar with
最初，当Evan刚开始的时候
um, initially Vite was an experiment on
Vite是一个仅Vue开发的工具
a development tool for Vue when Evan first started
当这个想法似乎奏效时
when an idea seems to be working out
尤雨溪 决定让它成为与框架无关的工具
Evan decided to make it framework-agnostic by
通过提取Vue的处理并制作插件
extracting Vue's handling into a plugin
并优化API
and polishing the API
然后我们有了今天的Vite
and then we have the Vite we know today
我得说Vite成功了
I'd say Vite success
结果远远超出了我的起初想象
turns out to be far beyond my initial imagination
现在它有了一个极其庞大的社区和生态系统
it now has an incredibly huge community and ecosystem
基本上，所有现代元框架都建立在它之上
basically, all modern meta-frameworks are built on top of it
并且跨多个框架和社区的合作
and collaboration across multiple frameworks and communities
真的非常出色
are really outstanding
还有很多其他因素使得
there are many other factors that make
Vite达到了今天的成就
Vite reach what it is today
但我会说，具有可扩展性
but I would say, being extendable
和框架无关性，确实拓宽了大门
and agnostic really widened the door
让社区加入和贡献
for the community to join and contribute
这部分的结论是，我们可以
the takeaway in this section is that we could
寻求打破交集的可能性
seek for the possibility of breaking the intersection
并使我们的项目变得通用
and make our projects universal
以下是我能想到的一些好处
here are some of the benefits I could think of
通过使我们的程序变得通用
by making our program universal
意味着我们可以接触到更大的用户群体并且
meaning we could reach out to a larger user base and
自然地我们会有更多的贡献者
naturally we would have a more contributor
加入我们并一起工作
to join the force and work together
而不是每个人都在做自己的解决方案
instead of everyone working on their own solutions that
不兼容彼此的解决方案
aren't compatible with each other
试图重构事物
trying to refactor things
因为通用性也帮助我们
because universals also help us to
修订我们的设计和抽象
revise our design and abstractions
并且我们通常可以最终得到一个更易维护和可扩展的架构
and often we could end up with a more maintainable and extendable architecture
最后，如果你的
and finally if your
项目开始得到更多用户的使用和各种需求
projects start to get more users usage from various need
任何对我们项目的改进都可能最终使得任何人在生态中受益
making any improvements in our projects could end up benefit anyone in the ecosystem
我们知道，通用性有很多好处
so we know that being universal has a lot of great benefits
但实际上，特定化也不是一件坏事
but actually being specific is also not a bad thing
我能想到的一个很好的例子是Nuxt
one of the great examples I could think of is Nuxt
Nuxt是一个Vue的特例
Nuxt is a metaphor that specific to Vue
在选择Nuxt的众多好处中
out of many benefits of choosing Nuxt
我想强调的一点是开发者体验
one thing I'd like to highlight is the developer experience
在Nuxt我们提供了很多功能，帮助你以更好更快地构建应用
in Nuxt we provide quite a lot features to help you build apps faster in a better organized way
我们有服务器端渲染以获得更好的用户体验和SEO
we have server side rendering for better user land performance and SEO
基于文件的路由以获得更好的代码结构
and file based routing for better organization
我们还拥有一个强大的模块系统用于集成
we also have a powerful module systems for integrations
以及Nuxt Devtools 等等
and also Nuxt Devtools etc
许多这些功能都是假设我们使用Vue并且有打包管道构建的
many of these are built with the assumption that we use Vue and has the bundling pipeline
Nuxt还使用Vite作为默认的开发服务器和打包器
Nuxt also use Vite as the default dev server and bundler
这意味着我们继承了Vite的优秀插件生态系统和快速的HMR
meaning that we inherit the great plugin ecosystem as well as the fast HMR from Vite
对于Nuxt而言，相比 Vite 它的需求更特殊
for Nuxt to be a bit specific than Vite
需要我们做更多很酷的功能和集成
allowing us to bring many cool features and integrations that
很难以通用的方式实现
will be hard to achieve in a universal way
我认为这就是为什么
I think that's why
有许多像Sveltekit、Astro和Solid 这样的特殊需求
that's also why we have many metaphor like Sveltekit, astro and Solid for different needs
在这里
and here
让我们看看Nuxt提供的一些功能
let's look into a couple of features that Nuxt provides
当我们谈论服务器端渲染和服务器API时
when we talk about server side rendering and server APIs
我们知道在某些情况下
we know that in some cases
我们需要服务器以某种形式与前端一起工作
we need a servers in some form to work together with the frontend
除了自托管的Node.js服务器之外
other than a self-hosted Node.js server
还有许多服务存在
there are also many services out there
例如Cloudflare、Netlify、Vercel等
for example like Cloudflare, Netlify, Vercel etc
为了充分利用每个提供者的潜力
to leverage the full potential of each provider
我们可能希望利用它们提供的
we might want to utilize the
边缘渲染和无服务器函数
edge rendering and serverless functions based on what they provide
需要注意的一点是
one thing to note is that
每个提供者都有自己的格式
each provider has its own format
有些还附带特定的工具
some might also come with a specific tooling
在Nuxt中，我们不希望我们的用户被限制在单一平台上
in Nuxt, we don't want our users to be stuck on a single platform
我们希望支持尽可能多的平台
we want to support as many platforms as possible building
因此我们构建了并支持自动检测
so we build and even supports auto detection
因此应用程序可以
so the app can be written
以同构方式编写并部署到各种平台上
isomorphically and deploy to various platforms
无需更改任何配置
without changing any configuration
然后我们意识到
and then we realized
这是一个
this is a problem
可能每个元框架都必须处理的问题
that's probably every meta framework has to deal with
它不必是Nuxt特有的
and it doesn't have to be Nuxt specific
所以我们将这些提取为一个标准工具，称为Nitro
so we extracted those into a standard tool called Nitro
它是一个通用的服务器构建工具，就像Vite，但用于服务器
it's a universal server builder and it's pretty much like Vite but for servers
使用Nitro处理服务器相关的细节
with Nitro taking care of the details of dealing with servers
它实际上需要Nuxt拥有一个更清晰的架构
it actually allows Nuxt to have a more clear architecture
用于处理服务器端渲染和API等
for handling server-side rendering and the APIs etc
由于Nitro是一个通用的服务器工具
and since Nitro is a general-purpose server tool
我们看到越来越多的元框架开始使用它
we see more and more meta framework starting to use it
所有新的框架
all new frameworks
开始在其上构建
start to build on top of it
我们有一个很受欢迎的Angular元框架Analog
we have analog a popular angular Metaphone
已经迁移到Nitro
has migrate to Nitro
Stacks是一个框架无关的框架
Stacks a firmwork agnostic for step framework
即使没有框架
even without a framework
我发现Nitro在构建纯API服务器并部署到运行时非常方便
I also find Nitro to be very handy to build a pure API server and to deploy on the edge run time
我们还听说有些框架正在迁移到Nitro
we also heard that there are some frameworks is in the process of migrating to Nitro
我会保密，直到他们正式发布
I'll keep it as secret until they do the announcement
类似地，在构建工具方面
similarly in terms of a bundling tools
Nuxt 2是基于webpack构建的
Nuxt 2 has built on top of webpack
所以在Nuxt 3中，我们希望保持兼容性和便于迁移
so in Nuxt 3 we want to keep that for compatibles and easy migration
同时我们也喜欢Vite的创新和开发体验
while we also love the innovations and develop experience on Vite
所以我们尝试支持
so we try to support
两种工具可以互换使用
both tools interchangeably
我们为两者提供了初步集成
we provide the first part of integration for both
webpack和Vite都预配置了Nuxt
webpack and Vite pre configured for Nuxt
所以理想情况下，应用程序在两者中都会一样工作
so ideally the app would work the same for both tools
然而我们知道
however we know that
这两者在架构和生态系统方面有很大的不同
the architectural as well as the ecosystems are quite different in them
例如，如果我们想在我们的功能中添加一些模块转换
for example if we want to add some transformations to some modules in our pipeline
这实际上意味着我们需要为每个插件格式实现逻辑
that actually means we need to implement the logic toys for each plugging format
这会使我们的工作量翻倍
that would basically doubles our work
以及会影响到社区模块的开发者们
as well as the effort for community modules to support them
所以这就是我们创建unplugin的初衷
that's theinitial motivation for us to create unplugin
一个通用
an universal
统一的插件接口，用于webpack和Vite
unified plugging interface for both webpack and Vit
有了它，我们
with that we are
能够节省很多处理每个工具的不对齐细节的工作
able to save a lot of effort sticking into the details of misalignment for each tool
并且由于unplugin被提取为一个独立工具
and since unplugin get extracted as a standalone tool
它也形成了自己的社区并扩大了范围
it also forms its own community and expand the scope
比如，支持Rollup、Esbuild和Rspack
uh to also support Rollup、esbuild and Rspack
未来可能会支持更多
and possibly more in the future
由于unplugin社区的努力
with the work done by the unplugin community
它也为Nuxt开始实验Rspack作为打包器开辟了道路
it also opens the door for Nuxt to start experimenting the support for Rspack as the bundler
这些只是两个例子
and those are just two examples
我们还有unjs社区提供的许多高质量工具
we also have unjs community that's providing many high quality tools
贯穿整个JavaScript生态系统
throughout the entire JavaScript ecosystem
Nitro和unplugin也是unjs社区的一部分
and we'll actually have Nitro and unplugin as part of the unjs community
我们还有一个Vite Node，从我们的服务器端代码执行器中诞生
we also have Vite Node made from our server side code executors
后来成为了Vitest的核心引擎
and later becomes the core engine of Vitest and make it possible
这些工具是从Nuxt的需求中产生的
those tools are created from Nuxt need
但后来我们提取它们并使其通用
but later we extract them and make them universal
它们形成了自己的社区和生态系统
they have formed their own community and ecosystem
可以惠及更广泛的用户和场景
that can benefit much wider range of users and scenario
Nuxt 只是一个给用户更好开发体验的框架
Nuxt can be the fireworks that s a bit specific by providing better experience
同时底层工具可以与其他框架和社区共享和合作
while the underlying tools can be shared and collaborate with other frameworks and community
这就是开源的神奇之处，不是吗
that's where make open source amazing isn't it
和我们谈论的集合交集不同的是
so the difference from set intersection we are talking about
我想称之为集合并集
I'd like to call it the set union
我们在追求通用部分
we struggle the universal part
扩大范围以发展社区
expanding the scope to grow the community
这最终也会回馈给我们自己
and also would eventually benefit back to ourselves
所以总结今天的主题
so to wrap up with today's topic
我们提出了一个想法
we bought up an idea
我称之为集合论
I would call it the set theory
由两个部分组成
and is composed with two sections
集合交集和集合并集
the set intersection and set union
在交集中
in the intersection
我们了解到我们不应该只把项目限制在一个小众领域
we Learned that we shouldn't limit our project to only be a niche spot
我们应该主动寻求使项目通用的可能性
we should proactively seeking for the possibility to making the project universal
通过破圈和扩大范围
by breaking the circles and enlarge our scopes
在并集中
and in the union
我们学习到即使事物存在本质区别即存在特殊性
we learned that even something have to be a little bit specific in order to achieve something great
我们仍然可以寻求
we could still seek for the
我们可以做出的潜在联合
potential union that we could make
以扩大社区和惠及整个生态系统
to expand the community and benefit the whole ecosystem
这就是关于合作和社区
and that's all about collaboration and community
我坚信开源是我们建设更美好世界的方式
I have a strong belief that open source would be the way for us to build a better world
我期待看到更多具有类似心态的开源项目
and I'm looking forward to see more and more open source building with similar mindset
这就是我演讲的全部内容
and that's all for my talk
谢谢
thank you